A Guide to the Virginia Volunteers, Muster-In Rolls, 1884-1919
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Volunteers, Muster-In Rolls, 1884-1919
Library of Virginia
32116
33 volumes
Virginia Volunteers
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Dept. of Military Affairs, Virginia National Guard, 15 June 1984.
Historical Information
The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1871 to provide for the organization of the Volunteer Militia of the State, and to repeal existing laws concerning the same. The militia, known as the Virginia Volunteers, was to consist of volunteers to be called into service in case of war, invasion, riots, etc. On March 17, 1884, another act was passed by the General Assembly to provide for the organization, maintenance and government of the Virginia volunteers. This act stipulated that the Virginia Volunteers should consist of no more than sixty companies of infantry, eight batteries of artillery, and ten troops of cavalry. The act also created the position of assistant inspector general whose duty was to muster and inspect each company, troop, or battery of volunteers once each year. The assistant inspector general then reported the result of these inspections to the adjutant general.
On April 25, 1898, the United States declared war on Spain. Immediately, the Secretary of War telegraphed J. Hodge Tyler, the Governor of Virginia, stating that three regiments of twelve companies of infantry were required for the war effort. The three regiments consisted of four companies from the 1st Regiment Infantry, eight companies from the 2nd Regiment Infantry, nine companies from the 3rd Regiment Infantry, eight companies from the 4th Regiment Infantry, two companies of the 3rd Battalion Infantry, and two companies of the 4th Battalion Infantry. With the addition of three new companies organized in Fairfax, Wytheville, and Lynchburg, these thirty-six companies comprised the three regiments which were designated the 2nd, 3rd, and 4th Virginia Infantry. Later, another regiment, designated the 6th Virginia Infantry, was created to fulfill the President's additional call for volunteers. The 1st and 2nd Battalions Infantry, consisting of colored soldiers, were mustered into this regiment. In addition, three divisions of naval volunteers were added in 1898 to the preexisting division established by an act of the General Assembly in 1894.
On April 29, 1899, the Adjutant General issued General Order No. 2 which disbanded and declared out of existence the 1st Brigade, the 1st through 4th Regiments Infantry, and the 1st through 4th Battalions Infantry. Only one company of infantry at Smithfield, one troop of cavalry at Surry, and the 1st Battalion Artillery remained in service as Virginia Volunteers. General Order No. 4, however, re-established 14 companies of infantry (unassigned to a regiment) in the Virginia Volunteers. In addition, three divisions of naval volunteers were added in 1898 to the preexisting division established by an act of the General Assembly in 1894 (this battalian disbanded in 1901). Following the war, the reorganization of the Virginia Volunteers continued with the assignment of new numbers to the regiments in order to distinguish those regiments who fought in the Civil and Spanish-American Wars. The 70th and 71st Infantry were the first of the new regiments organized in 1900 followed by the 72nd Infantry in 1905. A law was passed by the General Assembly on January 16, 1908, amending Section 306 of the Code of Virginia. This law stipulated that the organization, armament, and discipline of the Virginia militia or volunteers shall be the same as that of the regular and volunteer armies of the United States. In addition, the infantry regiments were again reorganized to reflect a tighter geographical grouping and were reassigned their pre-1898 designations (i.e. 1st, 2nd, & 4th Regiments). At this time, the first company of the Virginia Coast Artillery was formed to reinforce the regular army units in Hampton Roads. Three additional companies of Coast Artillery were organized by 1910, but the entire Coast Artillery Corps was disbanded in 1911 and not reorganized until 1916.
Following the draft into federal service and mobilization of the Virginia National Guard for Mexican Border Service and later war against Germany in 1917, a need arose to create a new militia force in Virginia. By order of Governor Henry C. Stuart, Adjutant General W.W. Sale issued a form letter authorizing the immediate formation of Home Defense organizations to be known as "Virginia State Volunteers" to serve during "the emergency." Two classes of Home Defense Organizations were created consisting of the Virginia State Volunteers and Virginia Home Guard. Lt. Col. Jo Lane Stern, State Inspector, was assigned the duty of organizing these volunteers. Companies of Virginia Volunteers were raised throughout the state including two battalions of infantry and over twenty individual companies. After the signing of the Armistice, most of these units disbanded or mustered out by 1920, although three companies passed over into the National Guard.
Scope and Content Information
The muster rolls from 1884-1915 record the following information: absent or present, number, rank, name, age at date of enlistment, date of enlistment or re-enlistment, term of enlistment, date of warrant, and remarks (e.g. sick, on furlough, absent without leave). Commissioned officers, non-commissioned officers, and privates are listed separately. A separate section of the muster roll lists losses since the last muster and includes those soldiers who were discharged, transferred, promoted, etc. The muster roll enumerates accessions and casualties since the last muster. Each muster is certified by the company commander. The company commander also includes an annual record of the company which states the number of drills & parades, battalion drills, and inspections by the company. A certificate by the mustering officer reports on uniforms, discipline, equipment, and records of the company. Lastly, each roll contains a recapitulation that enumerates those present and absent for duty.
The muster rolls from 1917-1918 record the name, age at date of enlistment, date of enlistment or re-enlistment, and remarks (usually records prior service). Privates are listed separately from commissioned officers and non-commissioned officers. A separate section of the muster roll lists losses since the last muster and includes those soldiers who were discharged, transferred, promoted, etc. The muster roll enumerates accessions and casualties since the last muster. Each muster is certified by the company commander. The company commander also includes an annual record of the company which states the number of drills & parades, battalion drills, and inspections by the company. A certificate by the mustering officer reports on uniforms, discipline, equipment, and records of the company. Lastly, each roll contains a recapitulation that enumerates those present and absent for duty.
The muster rolls from 1919 record the number, rank, name, age at date of enlistment, term of enlistment (emergency), date of warrant, and remarks (e.g. promoted, joined as recruit). Privates are listed separately from commissioned officers and non-commissioned officers. A separate section of the muster roll lists losses since the last muster and includes those soldiers who were discharged, transferred, promoted, etc. The muster roll enumerates accessions and casualties since the last muster. Each muster is certified by the company commander. The company commander also includes an annual record of the company which states the number of drills & parades, battalion drills, and inspections by the company. A certificate by the mustering officer reports on uniforms, discipline, equipment, and records of the company. Lastly, each roll contains a recapitulation that enumerates those present and absent for duty.
Volume I: Muster-In Rolls, 1884, contains muster rolls for the following units of the Virginia Volunteers: Field, Staff, and Band, 1st, 2nd, 3rd, & 4th Regiments, 1st Brigade; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "A" through "G"; 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 3rd Regt.; and Companies "B" through "H", 4th Regt.
Volume II: Muster-In Rolls, 1885, contains muster rolls for the following units: Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "C", "E" through "G", 2nd Regt. (Company B disbanded on October 17, 1885); Field, Staff, and Band, 3rd & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" & "B", "D" through "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885); Companies "B" through "D" & "F" through "H", 4th Regt. (Company A disbanded on October 17, 1885); Batteries "A" through "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Troops "A" through "C", 1st Battalion Cavalry; Richmond Light Artillery Blues Battalion; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A", "B", "D", & "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Virginia Guard (Lynchburg); Hill City Guards (Lynchburg); State Guard (Richmond); Libby Guard (Hampton); Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; Flipper Guards (Petersburg); Hannibal Guards (Danville); and the Staunton Light Guard.
Volume III: Muster-In Rolls, 1886, contains muster rolls for the following units: Field, Staff, and Band, 1st, 3rd, & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "E" & "F", 2nd Regt. (Companies A & B disbanded); Companies "A" & "B", "D" through "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885); Companies "B" through "H", 4th Regt. (Company A disbanded on October 17, 1885); Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Cavalry; Troops "A" through "C", 1st Battalion Cavalry; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A", "B", "D", & "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company C disbanded on February 26, 1887). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Petersburg Guards; State Guard (Richmond); Libby Guard (Hampton); Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; Flipper Guards (Petersburg); Hannibal Guards (Danville); and the Staunton Light Guard.
Volume IV: Muster-In Rolls, 1887, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st, 3rd, & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.,; Companies "B" & "C" and "E" & "F", 2nd Regt. (2nd Regiment disbanded on April 2, 1887); Companies "A" & "B", "D" through "H", "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "I", 4th Regt.; Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "C", "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Cavalry; Troops "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Cavalry; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "C", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company D disbanded on April 12, 1887); Companies "A", "B", "D", & "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company C disbanded on February 26, 1887). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Petersburg Guards; State Guard (Richmond); Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; Flipper Guards (Petersburg); Hannibal Guards (Danville); and the Staunton Light Guard.
Volume V: Muster-In Rolls, 1888, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.,; Companies "B" & "C" and "F", 2nd Regt. (2nd Regiment disbanded on April 2, 1887); Companies "A" & "B", "D" through "H", "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "I", 4th Regt.; Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Troops "B" through "D", 1st Battalion Cavalry; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "B" through "C", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company D disbanded on April 12, 1887); Companies "A" & "D", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company C disbanded on February 26, 1887). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Petersburg Guards; State Guard (Richmond); Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; and the Flipper Guards (Petersburg).
Volume VI: Muster-In Rolls, 1889, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.,; Companies "A" through "C", "E" through "G", 2nd Regt. (2nd Regiment disbanded on April 2, 1887 and reorganized on April 29, 1889); Companies "D" through "H", "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "K", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Cavalry; Troops "A" through "F", 1st Battalion Cavalry; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "C", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company D disbanded on April 12, 1887); Companies "A" & "D", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company C disbanded on February 26, 1887). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Petersburg Guards; Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; and the Flipper Guards (Petersburg).
Volume VII: Muster-In Rolls, 1890, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st, 2nd, & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "A" through "C", "E" through "H", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "B", "D" through "G", "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "K", 4th Regt.; Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "D", "F", 1st Cavalry Regt.; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "B", "D" through "E", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "C", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company D disbanded on April 12, 1887); Companies "A" & "D", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored) (Company C disbanded on February 26, 1887). There is also included the following unattached colored companies: Petersburg Guards; Petersburg Blues; Garfield Light Infantry; and the Flipper Guards (Petersburg).
Volume VIII: Muster-In Rolls, 1891, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 2nd, 3rd, & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "A" through "D", "F" through "G", "I", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "B", "E" through "H", "K", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "G", "I" through "K", 4th Regt.; Richmond Light Infantry Blues; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored). Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "F", 1st Cavalry Regt.
Volume IX: Muster-In Rolls, 1892, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st, 3rd, & 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "B", "D" through "E", "G" through "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A", "D" through "F", "H", 3rd Regt. (Company C disbanded on October 17, 1885; Company I disbanded on October 10, 1887); Companies "A" through "B", "D" through "I", "K", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "D", "F", 1st Cavalry Regt.; and the Richmond Light Infantry Blues.
Volume X: Muster-In Rolls, 1893, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st through 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "A", "C" through "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "B", "D" through "F", "H", 3rd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "C", "F" through "I" ("I" is mistakenly labeled "K"), 1st Cavalry Regt.; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Artillery; and the Richmond Light Infantry Blues. In addition, the Farmville Guard (changed to Co. C, 3rg Regt.), Franklin Light Infantry (changed to Co. I, 4th Regt.), Radford Rifles (changed to Co. B, 2nd Regt.), Roanoke Machine Works Guard (changed to Co. F, 2nd Regt in 1894), and Suffolk Light Infantry (changed to Co. F, 4th Regt.) are new companies which are listed separately at the back of this volume.
Volume XI: Muster-In Rolls, 1894, contains muster rolls for the following units: Field, Staff, and Band, 1st through 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "F", 1st Regt.; Companies "A" through "D", "F" through "H", "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "I", 3rd Regt.; Companies "A" through "L", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion (4th Bn. Inf.) (the RLIB was allowed to expand into a battalion by an act of the legislature in 1894); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "C", "H", and "K", 1st Cavalry Regt. (Troops D through G disbanded June 18, 1894); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); and Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored).
Volume XII: Muster-In Rolls, 1895, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade (pages missing); Field, Staff, and Band, 1st through 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "G", 1st Regt.; Companies "A", "C" through "D", "F" through "H", and "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 3rd Regt.; Companies "A" through "I", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, 3rd Battalion Infantry (the 3rd Battalion was organized in pursuance with an act of the General Assembly on March 31, 1894); Companies "A" & "B", 3rd Bn. Inf.; Field, Staff, and Band, Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion (4th Bn. Inf.) (the RLIB was allowed to expand into a battalion by an act of the legislature in 1894); Companies "A" & "B", Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "C", "G", and "K", 1st Cavalry Regt. (Troop D disbanded June 18, 1894); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "D", 1st Battalion Artillery; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); and Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored).
Volume XIII: Muster-In Rolls, 1896, contains muster rolls for the following units: General & Staff, 1st Brigade; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st through 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "G", 1st Regt.; Companies "A", "C" through "D", "F" through "H", and "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 3rd Regt.; Companies "A" through "I", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored); Field, Staff, and Band, 3rd Battalion Inf. (the 3rd Battalion was organized in pursuance with an act of the General Assembly on March 31, 1894); Companies "A" & "B", 3rd Bn. Inf.; Field, Staff, and Band, Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion (4th Bn. Inf.) (the RLIB was allowed to expand into a battalion by an act of the legislature in 1894); Companies "A" & "B", Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion; Virginia Zouaves (unattached company); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Cavalry Regiment; Troops "A" through "B", and "G", 1st Cavalry Regt. (Troop D disbanded June 18, 1894); Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; and Batteries "A" through "C", 1st Battalion Artillery.
Volume XIV: Muster-In Rolls, 1897, contains muster rolls for the following units: Field, Staff, and Band, 1st through 4th Regiments; Companies "A" through "G", 1st Regt.; Companies "A", "C" through "H", and "K", 2nd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 3rd Regt.; Companies "A" through "K", 4th Regt.; Field, Staff, and Band, 3rd Battalion Inf. (the 3rd Battalion was organized in pursuance with an act of the General Assembly on March 31, 1894); Companies "A" & "B", 3rd Bn. Inf.; Field, Staff, and Band, Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion (4th Bn. Inf.) (the RLIB was allowed to expand into a battalion by an act of the legislature in 1894); Companies "A" & "B", Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion; Field, Staff, & Band, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "C", 1st Battalion Artillery; Troops "A" & "B", Cavalry (1st Regt. Cavalry disbanded with the exception of Troops A & B in 1897); Field, Staff, and Band, 1st & 2nd Battalion Inf. (Colored); Companies "A" through "D", 1st Bn. Inf. (Colored); and Companies "A" through "E", 2nd Bn. Inf. (Colored).
Volume XV: Muster-In Rolls, 1898-1900, contains muster rolls for the following units: Field and Staff, 1st Regiment Infantry; Companies "D" through "F", 1st Regt.; Co. "H" (formerly 4th Regt. Inf.); Headquarters, 1st Battalion Artillery; Batteries "A" through "C", 1st Bn. Artillery; Divisions "A" through "D", 1st Naval Battalion; Troop B Cavalry (1st Regt. Cavalry disbanded with the exception of Troops A & B in 1897) (Troop A disbanded on April 23, 1898); West Augusta Guard (formerly Co. K, 1st Regt. Inf.); Co. I (formerly 4th Regt. Inf.); Alexandria Light Infantry (formerly Co. G, 1st Regt. Inf.); Roanoke Light Infantry (formerly Co. G, 2nd Regt. Inf.); Monticello Guards (formerly Co. D, 3rd Regt. Inf.); Piedmont Rifles; Companies "A" & "B", Richmond Light Infantry Blues Battalion; Richmond Grays (formerly Co. A, 1st Regt. Inf.); Walker Light Guard (formerly Co. B, 1st Regt. Inf.); Guard of the Commonwealth (formerly Co. C, 1st Regt. Inf.); Lynchburg Home Guard (formerly Co. E, 3rd Regt. Inf.); Old Dominion Guard (formerly Co. D, 1st Regt. Inf.); Farmville Guard (formerly Co. C, 3rd Regt. Inf.); Washington Guards (Co. L, 70th Regt. Inf.); Danville Light Infantry (Co. M, 70th Regt. Inf.); Lee Rifles (Co. A, 71st Regt. Inf.); Norfolk City Guard (Co. B, 71st Regt. Inf.); Huntingdon Rifles (Co. C, 71st Regt. Inf.); Peninsula Guards Co. D, 71st Regt. Inf.); Jackson Rifles (Co. E, 71st Regt. Inf.); Newport News Light Inf. (Co. G, 71st Regt. Inf.); Portsmouth Rifle Co. (Co. K, 71st Regt. Inf.); Old Dominion Guard of Portsmouth (Co. L, 71st Regt. Inf.); Greensville Guards (Co. M, 71st Regt. Inf.); and the Roanoke Blues.